<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief discourse of the present miseries of the kingdome: declaring by what practises the people of England have been deluded, and seduced into slavery, and how they have been continued therein, and by what meanes they may shake off that bondage, they are now enthraled under. / Written by a lover of his country, for the good of all such who are not contented to be slaves, but desire to live free-men.</title>
            <author>Lover of his country.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 76 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77431</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4583</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E467_24</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205268</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864685</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864685</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116917</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77431)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116917)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 75:E467[24])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief discourse of the present miseries of the kingdome: declaring by what practises the people of England have been deluded, and seduced into slavery, and how they have been continued therein, and by what meanes they may shake off that bondage, they are now enthraled under. / Written by a lover of his country, for the good of all such who are not contented to be slaves, but desire to live free-men.</title>
                  <author>Lover of his country.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In favor of the restoration of royal authority.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "8ber [i.e. October] 13th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Monarchy --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116917:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEF DISCOVRSE OF THE PRESENT <hi>MISERIES</hi> OF THE
KINGDOME: Declaring by what <hi>practiſes</hi> the <hi>people</hi> of
<hi>England</hi> have been <hi>deluded,</hi> and <hi>ſeduced</hi> into
<hi>Slavery,</hi> and how they have been <hi>continued</hi> therein, and by
what meanes they may <hi>ſhake off</hi> that <hi>bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage,</hi> they are now
<hi>enthraled</hi> under.</p>
            <p>Written by a lover of his <hi>Country,</hi> for the good of all
ſuch who are not contented to be <hi>ſlaves,</hi> but deſire to live
<hi>Free-men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:116917:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116917:2"/>
            <head>A briefe diſcourſe of the preſent <hi>Miſeries</hi> of
the <hi>Kingdome, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſad and deplorable condition of this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Kingdome, is
remarkeably evident to all intelligent perſons of all degrees, who have any
ſhare or intereſt in the Common-wealth; and by all thoſe who are honeſt
as much lamented. Yet every man is not ſenſible by what practices and
endeavours, our <hi>Lawes</hi> have been ſubvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or who have been the
Authors, and contrivers of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes miſerie: or at leaſt all men will
not ſeeme to underſtand, who have blowne the bellowes to kindle this
<hi>unnaturall War,</hi> which hath almoſt waſted and conſumed (although
not in their perſons, yet in their Eſtates) all the chief
<hi>Nobility,</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> of the Land. I have therefore out of my
zeale, to rectifie thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, who are not wilfully blinded by
their owne <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> and <hi>folly,</hi> written this enſuing
narrative; wherein is diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, how, and by what practiſes the Subjects
of <hi>England</hi> have been ſeduced, and made the unhappy inſtruments, to
contribute to their owne undoing: by which they may eaſily diſcerne, who
have been the Authors, and contrivers of their miſerie: and may hereby if
they become ſenſible of their paſt errours, finde a meanes to recover
their loſt <hi>Liberty,</hi> and redeeme themſelves from the
<hi>Slavery</hi> and <hi>Thraldome</hi> they have ſo long endured.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:116917:3"/>No man is ignorant in how happy a condition this
Kingdome was, before it was deſtroyed by this <hi>unhappy Parliament;</hi>
neither am I ſo partiall to the foregoing times, but that I could diſcerne
that there were faults then, for there was <hi>pride, ſloath,</hi> and
<hi>covet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe</hi> in ſome of the <hi>Clergie, Bribery</hi> and
<hi>corruption</hi> in ſome of the <hi>Judges, partiality</hi> and
<hi>ſelfe-intereſts</hi> in many <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> an aiming at an
exorbitant power in the Court, managed to <hi>His Majeſties</hi>
diſadvantage, by thoſe He imployed and truſted, who ſtudied their owne
ends and profits, without regard to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties <hi>Honour.</hi> Theſe
were the perſonall crimes of men, which could not juſtly occaſion
complaint againſt the whole frame and order of our ſetled conſtitution of
Government, yet the offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of theſe evill Miniſters, were accounted
great grievances, and multiplied in their number, and aggravated in their
nature, by thoſe <hi>Schiſmaticks,</hi> who could not make a rent and
diviſion in the <hi>Church Government,</hi> to which they were enemies,
becauſe they were curb'd and reſtrained by the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi>
power; &amp; hindred from introducing innovation into the Church, which they
could not effect, unleſſe they firſt beget a diſtraction in the
<hi>Civill Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi> And therefore there was no preſſure put upon
the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (and they counted all ſuch, whether legall, or illegall, if it
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned them in their purpoſes) but theſe <hi>Schiſmaticall</hi>
people, preſently put themſelves in oppoſition againſt it, and by that
gain'd an opinion amongſt the common ſort (who are ſtill of leaſt
underſtanding) that thoſe men were the chief <hi>Patriots:</hi> beleeving
according to their <hi>hypocriticall</hi> demenors, that they had no indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
ends, but aimed only at the good of the Common-wealth, and to maintaine the
<hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of the Subjects. Theſe men having by
theſe ſubtile inſinuations, crept into the good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the vulgar
people, the <hi>Clergie</hi> and <hi>Laity</hi> of the ſame Sect, magnifying
each the others integrity, and both deluding the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant people, the one by
an humble and feined <hi>piety,</hi> the other by pretending to a ſtrict
obſervation of the <hi>Laws,</hi> in ſo much that the common people
imagined that there was no way left to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the golden age, but by bringing
theſe men into power and Authority, and to make them the directors, and
Governours both in Church and State. Then was raiſed a generall complaint
that all things were out of order, by reaſon we had no <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:116917:3"/>called, but how to reduce <hi>His Majeſty</hi> to a
neceſſity to call a <hi>Parliament,</hi> and to make that neceſſity
ſuch, as that He might not be able to diſſolve that <hi>Parliament:</hi>
this was the ſtudy and practice of theſe underminers of our happy and
peaceable Government.</p>
            <p>The people of <hi>England</hi> had been ſo long inur'd to Peace,
and with it were growne ſo rich, that it was difficult to ſtir them up to
any <hi>commotion</hi> or <hi>Rebellion:</hi> And therefore there muſt be
ſome way found out by His Majeſties owne Inſtruments, and Miniſters of
State to diſturbe the Kingdome; and no man was found ſo fit for this as the
<hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> whoſe zeale to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the
dignity of the <hi>Proteſtant Church</hi> within His Majeſties Dominions,
by reducing it to an uniformity, and decency in Gods worſhip, and by
endeavouring to increaſe the <hi>Wealth</hi> of it, that ſo the
<hi>Clergie</hi> might not become contemptible, was cheriſt in theſe pious
endeavours, and became ſo paſſionate in the purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance thereof, being I
am afraid a little tranſported with the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of being ſtiled the
<hi>author</hi> of ſo <hi>glorious</hi> a worke, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mature
conſideration he ſwallowed all propoſals, that he imagined might conduce
to ſo good an end: And ſo became unfortunately engaged in the reforming of
the <hi>Scottiſh Kirke,</hi> by endeavouring to conforme it to the
<hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of
<hi>England.</hi> In this undertaking I am confident his <hi>Lordſhip</hi>
had no end that aimed at any thing but <hi>Gods worſhip,</hi> but I have been
on very good grounds aſcertain'd that thoſe who put his <hi>Lordſhip</hi>
on this work, had an intention thereby to deſtroy the <hi>Biſhops</hi> in
that Kingdome; that ſo they might be diſpoſers of the Churches patrimony.
This gave the firſt riſe to our miſeries, for the <hi>Scots</hi>
imediately oppoſe our <hi>Lyturgie,</hi> branding it as <hi>Popiſh,</hi>
and <hi>Superſtitious,</hi> that <hi>Lyturgie</hi> which in the time of
<hi>Queene Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> when She protected them againſt the Invaſions
of the <hi>French,</hi> they embraced with all reverence and
thankefulneſſe, and made uſe thereof in their Churches, as long as they
had need of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Protection, and then it was neither
<hi>Popiſh</hi> nor <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious,</hi> but a moſt holy worſhip,
divinely compoſed for the decent and true honour of God: but they had not
then been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in Mr. <hi>Calvins</hi> Doctrine, or at leaſt knew
not how to wreſt it, and make uſe of it to throw off <hi>obedience</hi> to
<hi>Kings,</hi> as<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116917:4"/>the true <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> had
taught them to throw off the uſurpt <hi>Authority</hi> of the
<hi>Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cardinall Richlieu,</hi> who was undoubtedly the moſt
vigilant, and wiſeſt Councellour of this latter age; who induſtriouſly
ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died his <hi>Princes</hi> advancement, and enlargements of his
Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and had been long ſtudying and contriving to diſturbe the Peace
of <hi>England,</hi> and watching every opportunity to doe it, for he well knew
as long as the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England</hi> enjoyed Peace, he held the
ballance of this part of Chriſtendome, and by joyning with any Prince in
oppoſition to the <hi>French King,</hi> would be able at any time to give a
ſtop to his increaſe of <hi>Empery,</hi> and reſtraine his enlargement of
Dominion, which this <hi>Cardinall</hi> aymed at: And for that cauſe he
covetouſly embraced this occaſion offered by the <hi>Scots</hi> refuſall
of our Booke of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently endeavours to
inſinuate the Auncient League between their Nations, how willing the
<hi>French</hi> would be to aſſiſt them in the defence of their
<hi>Religion, Laws</hi> and <hi>Liberties;</hi> But the Language which the
<hi>Scots</hi> beſt underſtood was the <hi>French crownes,</hi> for that
wiſe States man well knew, how little gold was generated in that cold
<hi>climate,</hi> and how affected that Nation was to that met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, for he
believed they might be purchaſed not onely to forfeit their
<hi>Allegeance</hi> but to ſell their <hi>God</hi> for that coyne. And
therefore he ſubtilely diſperſed his <hi>crownes</hi> amongſt their
<hi>poor Nobility,</hi> who received them with condition of <hi>Rebellion,</hi>
but yet durſt not enter openly into an hoſtile oppoſition of their
<hi>Kings</hi> commands, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they were aſſured of a party in
<hi>England,</hi> and therefore the <hi>Puritanicall</hi> party of this
Kingdome muſt be tamper'd withall, and accordingly were, and found right for
their turne; but theſe were but of the meaner ſort of people, and ſuch as
were not able to raiſe any conſiderable power to countenance their
underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings. And therefore it was neceſſary that ſome eminent
<hi>Lords</hi> ſhould be drawne into the Plot, of which there were not many,
that were <hi>Puritannically</hi> affected, and therefore they muſt ſeeke
to gaine ſuch who were diſcontented, becauſe they were not countenanced,
and enjoyed <hi>offices</hi> and <hi>honours</hi> at <hi>Court,</hi> to which
their ambitions prompted them. This was by the induſtry of theſe men
effected, and accordingly divers of the Nobillty were wrought upon to be of
this party, of which I beleeve divers of<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116917:4"/>them who look't not
into the depth of this Conſpiracy, have ſince heartily repented; ſeeing,
and now knowing, what inſtruments they were made, to contribute to the ruine
of this Kingdome. But they underſtood <hi>His Majeſty</hi> had money in his
purſe, and was beforehand with the world, and untill that was waſted and He
become poor, there was no hope of bringing Him to comply with their ends, and
therefore there muſt be a <hi>ſhew</hi> of <hi>War,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a
<hi>reall War,</hi> and for this reaſon <hi>His Majeſty</hi> muſt be
perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to carry an Army to the borders of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to compell
the <hi>Scots</hi> to conformity, and there He muſt have inſtruments to
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade Him to lye ſtill, untill His ſtock of money was ſpent,
Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and making, and receiving overtures of Peace, which at laſt was
concluded, and the obſervation thereof ſolemnely proteſted to continue
ſo long, untill their <hi>Brethren</hi> in <hi>England</hi> were ready to
aſſiſt them, and then the Religious <hi>Scots</hi> had liberty to breake
all <hi>Oathes,</hi> and <hi>Proteſtations,</hi> and <hi>Rebell</hi> againe.
And ſo ſhortly after they enter into <hi>England,</hi> with a pretence to
<hi>Petition</hi> His Majeſty, but not to <hi>fight,</hi> but for their
ſafety. This Petition muſt be preſented by an <hi>Army,</hi> and this
<hi>Army</hi> muſt poſſeſſe themſelves of <hi>Townes</hi> in
<hi>England,</hi> and muſt have all things granted unto them, which they
could poſſibly deſire, within the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and this
muſt be confirmed unto them by <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> wherein
<hi>His Majeſty</hi> muſt diveſt Himſelfe of all <hi>Regall
pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> and give up all into the hands of His <hi>Scottiſh</hi>
Subjects, to be at their diſpoſall, which could not have been an ill
bargaine for His Majeſty, if He had had but ſome tye upon them to make good
the compact; for if an <hi>Earth-quake</hi> ſhould ſwallow up thoſe that
are perfidious of that Nation, it could be no loſſe unto the
<hi>Crowne</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> unto which they have ever been falſe and
burthen-ſome: For what was there wanting to that Nation, that they could
deſire from their native <hi>King?</hi> His bounty, affection, and protection
they were ſufficiently ſenſible of, if they could be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of
benefits, but nothing can obliege them to hold their <hi>faith,</hi> or become
<hi>gratefull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>Scots</hi> being in a hoſtile manner entred the
Kingdome, whom all good Subjects were bound to oppoſe and reſiſt; it was
ſo far from that, that thoſe Souldiers which His Majeſtie raiſed for
that purpoſe were diſheartned, and diſcouraged, in their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116917:5"/>and their Officers branded with the names of
<hi>Papiſts,</hi> and the Souldiers encouraged to mutiny againſt their
Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Scots</hi> being <hi>Invaders</hi> were welcomed, and to
make it good that they were Invited into the Kingdome, they were well
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſed for their paines. And no doubt this money was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them that
they might be ready on all occaſions to enter the Kingdome againe when the
<hi>Parliament</hi> ſhould call for them to ſecond and aſſiſt them in
their attempts againſt His Majeſty: For truely now the <hi>Parliament</hi>
have a very faire pretence, to challenge the ſame grants from His Majeſty
that the <hi>Scots</hi> have obtained, and they are ſure of their
<hi>Brethrens</hi> aſſiſtance, for they deſire that this Kingdome
ſhould be as far engaged in <hi>Rebellion</hi> as themſelves; for by that
being become equall ſharers in iniquity, they are thereby mutually obliged to
potect, and preſerve each other againſt the power of the <hi>King,</hi>
whom they are bound to oppoſe and ſuppreſſe, leſt His juſtice
enabled by power, ſhould overtake and puniſh their <hi>Trayterous
Rebellion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Scots</hi> being now gone out of <hi>England,</hi> and His
Majeſty ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and there according to His
promiſes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed all by <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> as
aforeſaid, He returned hither to aſſure His ſubjects here that He was
willing to do for them what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they could demand for the good of the
Common-wealth, and by the preſidents of having already condiſcended unto
more then ever any of His Anceſtors did for the Subjects, they are not at all
ſtirred up to a <hi>gratitude</hi> for His grace and favour already
conferr'd, but are thereby encouraged to make greater and higher
<hi>demands,</hi> and muſt now inveſt themſelves with all <hi>Regall</hi>
power and authority, and <hi>His Majeſty</hi> muſt be but a
<hi>cipher,</hi> whilſt they rule, governe, order and diſpoſe all things
at their pleaſure. And that they may the better gull and abuſe the people,
and ſo lead them on to beleeve in them, they muſt in generals traduce the
whole government, the <hi>Church</hi> they muſt beſpatter with
<hi>Popery,</hi> and therein all decency muſt be accounted
<hi>Superſtition,</hi> and the <hi>Biſhops</hi> who laboured for
uniformity, and puniſht <hi>non-conformiſts,</hi> muſt be branded with
the names of <hi>Popiſh innovators,</hi> and the chief crimes laid to their
chare was <hi>Church Ornaments,</hi> which they ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>ragges</hi> of
the <hi>whore</hi> of <hi>Babell.</hi> Sure if God had commanded
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116917:5"/>theſe reformers to have built the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> or
the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> they would not have obeyed him, but told him he was
<hi>Popiſhly</hi> affected, and would have built him a <hi>Temple</hi> after
their owne fancies and imaginations.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Church</hi> being now the object of their furious zeale,
the wiſdome of this grave Senate is not bound to particularize the faults
therein, for ſo they might come to be diſputed, and might either in the
reaſon and opinion of the people prove no faults, or elſe by that courſe
it might onely produce a <hi>Reformation,</hi> but that was not the
<hi>Parliaments</hi> aime, for they indeavoured to throw the whole Kingdom into
combuſtion, eſpecially the <hi>Church Government,</hi> that muſt be
deſtroyed, that ſo they may therein frame a new <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topian</hi>
government, agreeing with their phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique zeale: The people greedy of
<hi>novelties,</hi> willingly embrace &amp; entertaine theſe changes, and
with an eaſie credulity, beleeve all ſcandalous reports that are by theſe
mens factors and abettors, raiſed to calumniate the <hi>Church,</hi> they
doubt not if theſe men tell them ſo, but that there lurkes
<hi>Idolatry</hi> in a <hi>Tipet</hi> or a <hi>Surplice,</hi> and if theſe
men incite the madde multitde thereunto, they will preſently diſroable
their Miniſters of their decent veſtments, and for no other cauſe then
that they are conformable to the eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed Government of the
<hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> they will aſſiſt to drive them from
their Cures, and without any legall authority, to diveſt them of what they
are poſſeſt of by the <hi>Lawes</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and the
<hi>Realme:</hi> if any Inhabitant within thoſe Pariſhes where theſe
enormities were committed, was ſo conſcientious as that he would not adhere
to theſe exorbitant courſes, he was ſure to be preſently branded with
the name of <hi>Papiſt,</hi> or at leaſt <hi>Popiſhly affected,</hi> and
that alone was ſufficient to declare, that he was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected to the
Parliament proceedings, and muſt be preſently new <hi>Chriſtened</hi> by
his <hi>Parliament god-fathers,</hi> with the nick-name of <hi>Malignant,</hi>
and <hi>Delinquent.</hi> And if this new named creature doth not forthwith
ſeale up his lips, and not dare to ſpeake or mutter againſt thoſe, who
proſecute theſe <hi>illicit acts,</hi> a <hi>Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> ſhal be
ready to fetch him to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> where in cuſtody he ſhall
attend at an extraordinary charge their honours leiſure, who by reaſon of
the high and weighty affaires of the Kingdome, cannot admit to hear ſo petty
a complaint, untill this poor <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:116917:6"/>purſe
growes empty, and the <hi>Meſſenger</hi> hath ſufficiently drained his
pockets; and then peradventure he will carry him before a <hi>Committee,</hi>
where he ſhall be examined upon captions <hi>gueres,</hi> whereby he may
entrap himſelfe, he ſhall neither know his <hi>accuſer,</hi> nor his
<hi>accuſation,</hi> but he ſhall be told in generall, that he is a notable
oppoſer of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and for that he ſhall be ſure to be
committed to ſome <hi>Priſon,</hi> that ſo his example of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment
may terrifie others from daring &amp; preſuming to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men. With
this manner of proceeding, the moſt rationall men, who diſcovered and
diſliked theſe practiſes, were deterr'd from oppoſing them, and thoſe
of the vulgar and ordinary ranke of people, were perſwaded by other
arguments, which were more prevalent on their underſtandings, which was
<hi>impunity</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit:</hi> for they were informed that they
ſhould neither pay <hi>Tithes,</hi> nor be be <hi>ſubject</hi> to
<hi>Eccleſiaſticall Courts:</hi> by this they were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to take part
with theſe new <hi>Reformers.</hi> But as yet the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi>
durſt not declare againſt the <hi>Common-Praier Booke,</hi> for they
thought the people were too well inclined to that forme of Worſhip, to be
ſuddenly deprived thereof: And therefore they declare that they intend not to
aboliſh the Booke of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> but by authority confirme the
uſe of it throughout the Kingdome, and withall they tell the people that it
is a ſcandall raiſed by the <hi>Malignant</hi> party to make them odious,
to report that they intended any ſuch thing as to take away the
<hi>Common-Prayer Booke,</hi> onely there may be ſome things in it that may
be fit to be reform'd; which hereafter with the advice of an
<hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly</hi> of <hi>Reverend Divines</hi> they meane to performe: Yet
at the ſame time they connive at ſuch Miniſters as leave it off, and
ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſcandalous <hi>pamphleteers</hi> to traduce that Sacred
<hi>Lyturgie,</hi> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted from the <hi>Scripture,</hi> Compoſed by the
moſt Reverend, Learned, and pious <hi>Divines,</hi> and <hi>ſealed</hi> by
the <hi>bloud</hi> of <hi>Martyres:</hi> By theſe Inſtruments they firſt
undermine it, and afterward when they have occaſion to make uſe of their
<hi>Scotch Brethren</hi> to Conquer the Kingdome, then they are fitted with a
packt Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, that muſt declare againſt the Booke of
<hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> as <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh</hi> and <hi>Superſtitious,</hi>
that ſo they may introduce a thing called a <hi>Directory,</hi> that may
bring them to a conformity with their <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> in <hi>Doctrine,
Worſhip,</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:116917:6"/>Now give me leave to tell you by the way, that
theſe men who have ſo univerſally changed, and altered the ſetled, and
profeſſed <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> within this Kingdome, abuſed the
people with telling them that <hi>His Majeſty</hi> by the advice of His
<hi>evill Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors,</hi> and aſſiſtance of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi>
meant to <hi>change</hi> and <hi>alter Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> by throwing a
ſuppoſed infamy on <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> which they really intended
afterwards to effect themſelves, as is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt by the ſequell, for they
have abſolutely changed our <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>His Majeſty</hi>
remaines a conſtant perſeverer in the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the old
eſtabliſhed forme, both of <hi>Doctrine, Worſhip,</hi> and
<hi>Diſcipline;</hi> and I will be bold to affirm, that the Kingdome is
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt if not altogether, the unparallel'd preſident that have
<hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> againſt their <hi>King,</hi> and fought, and deſtroyed
the <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> of their Kingdome, becauſe they
will not conſent to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce the <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Laws</hi> of
another <hi>Nation,</hi> and of ſuch a Nation as <hi>Scotland,</hi> whoſe
people for the moſt part are not yet <hi>civilized,</hi> and for their
<hi>rudeneſſe,</hi> and <hi>poverty,</hi> are the ſcorne and contempt of
all <hi>Chriſtendome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This could not be that the gallant <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhould be
ſo delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but that for their ſins God hath infatuated them to be
ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of their owne deſtruction.</p>
            <p>This much by way of digreſſion; The <hi>Parliament</hi> now
find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the people ſo apt to beleeve all that they ſuggeſt, they begin
to decline, not onely againſt <hi>His Majeſty</hi> in relation to
<hi>Religion,</hi> but alſo accuſe Him of <hi>miſgovernment</hi> in
<hi>Civill affaires,</hi> but like the reſt, they will not ſtrike
point-blanke at <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> but wound Him through His
<hi>Miniſters</hi> ſides, telling the people, that He hath been miſled by
<hi>evill Councellors,</hi> and thereupon they frame a <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi>
which I may call an appeale to the people, whereby they aſperſe and traduce
<hi>His Majeſty</hi> by enumerating all the <hi>preſſures,</hi> and
ſuppoſed <hi>grievances,</hi> wherewith the Subjects have been burthened,
ſince <hi>His Majeſty</hi> came to the Crowne, and they therein proceed
ſo far as to accuſe <hi>His Majeſties intentions,</hi> ſaying that He
intended to put an <hi>Exciſe</hi> upon his people. Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man imagined that
they did this to declare to the world what Taxes the Subjects groaned under,
and no man could ſuppoſe that the <hi>Parliament</hi> would multiply and
encreaſe theſe grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and that they would impoſe an
<hi>Exciſe</hi> upon the people,<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116917:7"/>and ſo would induce that
into <hi>Act,</hi> which they pretend onely was <hi>intentionally</hi> in
<hi>His Majeſty,</hi> but time ſhewes us otherwiſe, for now the little
fingers of theſe Councellors are weightier in oppreſſing the Subjects,
then the loynes of <hi>His Majeſties Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Free-borne Subject muſt be impriſoned, diſſeiſed of
his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and no Legall cauſe ſhewne, <hi>Taxes</hi> impoſed, all
things ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged by <hi>Arbitrary</hi> power, and no appeale but to them that do
the injuſtice, this is part of the preſent miſery we groane under, but
more of this in its due place.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Parliament</hi> finding an inclination in <hi>His
Majeſty</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form all that is amiſſe, and willing to comply with
His <hi>Parliament</hi> in all that they can propoſe for the good of the
people, they grow fearfull that if <hi>His Majeſty</hi> be ſuffered to
comply with them ſo faſt, all that is amiſſe in the Common-wealth will
be reform'd too ſoone, and then there will be no worke for them, but they
muſt returne home, and become private men againe, which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their
intentions; for they reſolve to <hi>Lord</hi> it over their <hi>fellow
Subjects</hi> perpetually, which they cannot doe, unleſſe they devolve the
Kingdome into greater miſeries and diſtractions, by contriving a <hi>Civill
War</hi> within the bowels thereof: for the effecting of which, they uſe all
their art and induſtry to inſlave the people, by pretending that there is a
<hi>Malignant party</hi> in the Kingdome of <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and ſuch as
are <hi>Popiſhly affected,</hi> who are <hi>machinating</hi> treacherous
plots againſt them, by deſtroying of this glorious <hi>Parliament,</hi>
which intends ſo much good to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; and in the ruine of this
<hi>Parliament,</hi> to bury all hopes of future redreſſe of our
grievances.</p>
            <p>Theſe <hi>feares</hi> and <hi>jealouſies</hi> are fomented
amongſt the people, by their active inſtruments, who are eſpecially
thoſe of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and theſe by their pretended ſanctity of
life eaſily gained credit amongſt their ſimple auditors, beſides ſuch
as are divulgers of theſe reports, are directed to inſinuate, that <hi>His
Majeſty</hi> hath a hand in theſe contrivances, by which obliquity He
muſt be repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented as the object of the peoples fear, who ought to be the
protector of them and their Lawes, and they the ſecurity of His Power and
Perſon: By this, diſtruſt of <hi>His Majeſty</hi> being begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and
nouriſht amongſt the people, <hi>His Majeſties</hi> Perſon, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116917:7"/>with His <hi>Royall Conſort</hi> and <hi>Children,</hi>
are expoſed to all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnie and reproach; that ſo they may become
contemptible. Yet notwithſtanding all theſe practiſes, which were the
contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of particular plotters in both Houſes: yet there was a party of
honeſt able Gentlemen in the Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> and the
<hi>Biſhops</hi> and ſome <hi>Noble Lords</hi> in the Houſe of
<hi>Peeres,</hi> that croſt and thwarted the proceedings of this violent
party. How to remove theſe was now the great endeavour, and the
<hi>Biſhops</hi> they muſt firſt be thruſt out of the Houſe of
<hi>Lords,</hi> and the better to effect this, the people they muſt be
ſtirr'd up to <hi>Petition</hi> the Houſe of <hi>Commons,</hi> that the
<hi>Prelates</hi> who by their <hi>Votes</hi> in <hi>Parliament</hi> hindred
the intended <hi>Reformation,</hi> might by an <hi>Act</hi> of
<hi>Parliament</hi> be excluded out of the Houſe, and their <hi>Votes</hi>
taken away.</p>
            <p>And to the end that theſe people might not erre in the forme or
manner of Petitioning, they had good friends in the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> that
could penne their Petitions according to the ſenſe of the Houſe: theſe
Petitioners were commonly attended by a tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuous rabble of the City and
Suburbes, who were ſummoned to meet together for that purpoſe, and although
they came toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and flockt to the Houſes, more like an unlawfull
aſſembly of riotous, and mutinous perſons, who imperiouſly
<hi>demanded,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then humbly <hi>Petitioned</hi> for what they
deſired, and therefore for their manner of comming, rather deſerved to be
reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded then cheriſht, yet they were welcomed, and thankt for their
great care of the Common-wealth, and encourag'd to draw to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in ſuch
unlawfull aſſemblies.</p>
            <p>The Bill being now formed for the excluding the <hi>Biſhops</hi>
out of the Houſe, they preſſe <hi>His Majeſty</hi> to ſign it, and
that they may worke Him thereunto, they make uſe of all thoſe Inſtruments
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Him, who are either afraid to be laſht by their exorbitant power, or
elſe are deſirous to partake with them in their wayes, and theſe who are
truely the <hi>evill Councellors,</hi> obtaine of <hi>His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> to
paſſe this <hi>Bill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I wiſh with my ſoule His Majeſty had never been betrayed by
theſe evil Inſtruments to doe ſo ill an act as to deprive the
<hi>Church</hi> of that power next under Him ſhould govern and protect it,
and by their conſent to wholſome Lawes in <hi>Parliament</hi> preſerve
their flocks from the ravenous Wolves that have ſince devoured them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:116917:8"/>I am no <hi>Lawyer</hi> to determine how
eſſentiall a part of the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> the <hi>Biſhops</hi> were,
but I believe they were one of the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates</hi> that made up that great
<hi>body,</hi> and this I am ſure is conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to reaſon, for if each
Member of the Common-wealth be obliged to obey the <hi>Lawes</hi> made in that
Convention, becauſe they conſent unto them by thoſe who are preſent at
the making of thoſe Lawes as being Perſons choſen by them by whoſe
Votes they oblige themſelves, I know no reaſon that the <hi>Clergy</hi> who
are ſo eminent a part of the Common-wealth, ſhould not have fit perſons
by them choſen to ſit and Vote likewiſe in the Houſe, by whom their
conſent unto all Lawes might be included.</p>
            <p>And it will appear a ſtrange irregular courſe in the opinion
of foraine Nations, and that which will be a diſhonour and a diſparagement
unto this Kingdome, that the <hi>doctrine</hi> and <hi>diſcipline</hi> of our
<hi>Church,</hi> is ſubverted, and that we have in a manner a new Religion
framed, and no <hi>Clergy-man</hi> hath either an <hi>affirmative</hi> or a
<hi>negative Vote</hi> in the compoſure; an <hi>Aſſembly of Divines</hi>
being pickt out and packt together by no lawfull authority, and onely made
uſe of to colour out and countenance the acts of thoſe who are altogether
<hi>Lay-men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It will ſeem ſtrange hereafter when theſe proceedings
ſhall be maturely heard and debated, that it ſhould appear that a
buſineſſe of ſo high a nature as the diſpoſſeſſing the
<hi>Biſhops</hi> of their juſt rights ſhould be tranſacted, and that
thoſe who are <hi>parties</hi> ſhould be made their <hi>Judges,</hi> to
condemn without hearing thoſe who are ſo eminently their Superiours both in
degree and dignity: but it is now too apparent to all the world what it was
that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked this violent and irregular proſecution, the end being that
theſe Reformers might rob the Church of that patrimony which the piety of
their Aunceſtors had inveſted the <hi>Biſhops</hi> withall.</p>
            <p>And it will be well if the <hi>legiſlative</hi> power which
theſe men exerciſe can ſecure them from being guilty of
<hi>ſacriledge,</hi> and quit them at the dreadfull Tribunall from horrid
impiety.</p>
            <p>Thoſe honeſt and able Noblemen and Gentlemen who were choſen
and truſted by their Countries, and whoſe tender conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences ſcrupled
at theſe injurious and impious proceedings, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the dictate of
their reaſons diſſented from theſe unjuſt and irregular actions,
theſe were traduced amongſt the people as<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116917:8"/>members
Popiſhly affected, and not fit to continue in the Houſes.</p>
            <p>And to deter them the more, the rabble &amp; ſcum of the people
were brought down often to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and there were taught to
know thoſe men that oppoſed their <hi>Faction,</hi> and to revile them with
ſcurilous and opprobrious language, and ſo to menace them as they thought
it not ſafe for them to ſtay longer in the Houſes, eſpecially after
they had with the like <hi>Tumults</hi> driven away <hi>His Majeſty</hi> from
<hi>White-hall,</hi> the Protectour of them and the Lawes being chaſed out of
the Towne, there was little ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity left for thoſe Subjects who did
deſire to regulate their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by the Law, when their King that ſhould
maintain the Law, and unto whom all His Subjects did owe and had ſworne
<hi>obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> could not ſecure Himſelf from the inſolence and
violence of the inraged <hi>multitude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sure all this while the people were in a dreame, or elſe they
could not have been drawn ſo madly to violate all Law, and to contribute to
their owne undoing.</p>
            <p>For, by driving away theſe ſober and temperate men from the
<hi>Parliament,</hi> and <hi>His Majeſty</hi> from their protection, they put
all Power and Authority into the hands of furious <hi>Schiſmatiks,</hi> and
ſubmitted themſelves and their Eſtates to be diſpoſed by them,
whoſe <hi>phrenaticall</hi> ſpirits never knew temper and moderation in any
of their actions.</p>
            <p>By their Votes and Ordinances the Kingdome is immediately throwne
into all diſorder and diſtemper, unlimited <hi>tyrannous</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall
authority uſurpt by Subjects, who like <hi>Phaëton</hi> gotten into the
<hi>Suns Chariot</hi> ſet all the world on fire, it never hapning
other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe but that when ſuch unskilfull Pilots get to the helme, all
Paſſengers are ſhipwrackt on the rocks. So it fell out with theſe men,
as how could it be otherwiſe imagined, that <hi>Shop-keepers</hi> and poor
mechanique <hi>Tradeſ-men</hi> (for ſuch were the major part that were left
in the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi>) ſhould be able to manage and diſpoſe
the great affaires of the Kingdome. I doe not ſay that all the <hi>Houſe of
Commons</hi> conſiſted of ſuch, for there were ſome cunning Contrivers
left in the Houſe, who either out of malice to the preſent ſetled
Government, or envy that they were not preferred to eminent Places and Offices
at Court, at which their ambitions aymed, who guided and governed the reſt of
the<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116917:9"/>Members to conſent unto, and Vote what they deſigned
for the diſturbance of the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>Theſe having driven away <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> and alſo
their <hi>fellow Members</hi> that oppoſed them, it was now neceſſary
that they ſhould ſtill infuſe <hi>fears</hi> and <hi>jealouſies</hi>
into the hearts of the people, thereby to prevent that they may not return unto
their wits and ſetled judgment: For, then their Treaſons would be unmask'd,
and their Plots and contrivances diſcovered, and then the people would fall
upon them as the Authours of their miſery.</p>
            <p>To avoid this, theſe cunning Artiſts ſhifted the ſcene,
and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the common Proverb, <hi>cried Whore firſt.</hi> And
divulged that <hi>His Majeſty</hi> intended to raiſe <hi>War</hi> againſt
His <hi>Parliament,</hi> whereas the truth was, they intended to raiſe a
<hi>War</hi> againſt <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> and to this purpoſe all the
<hi>lies</hi> that the <hi>Devill</hi> the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of <hi>lies</hi> could
invent, were printed and publiſhed by their allowance, <hi>Papiſts</hi>
every where muſtered <hi>inviſible Armies</hi> under ground, and <hi>forain
Forces</hi> were landed in every Port, and daily intelligence pretended to be
brought to the Houſe of ſtrange <hi>Maſſacres</hi> intended for the
cutting the throats of all their <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> eſpecially the moſt
eminent, they were aymed at to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed: and yet all theſe pretences
could hardly prevaile with the people inured to long <hi>peace</hi> and
<hi>quiet</hi> to put themſelves into Armes, and therefore they would not
relie on the giddy <hi>multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,</hi> although they had incenſed them with
ſtrange malitious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, which was, that <hi>His Majesties Commiſſions
of Array</hi> which He directed into the ſeverall Counties of the Kingdome to
mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the Forces thereof for the preſervation of their <hi>peace</hi>
accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to an auncient and knowne Law, was intended for their ruine and
deſtruction, and thereby to ſubject them unto a <hi>tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> and
<hi>arbitrary</hi> power, whereby they ſhould be robb'd of their Eſtates,
and enſlaved in their perſons. This rumour wrought much with the ignorant
multitude, yet not ſo much as that the <hi>Parliament</hi> would build upon
this foundation, an aſſurance of protection from the people, but would make
uſe of the <hi>peoples affections</hi> and <hi>inclinations</hi> towards them
as a good ſecond to their maine ſupport, which was an Army of mercinary
Souldiers, raiſed by <hi>His Majeſties</hi> conſent, to ſuppreſſe
the <hi>Iriſh Rebellion,</hi> but em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed by theſe men to fight againſt
<hi>his Majeſty,</hi> &amp; upon the fore-mentioned<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116917:9"/>pretences to deſtroy Him and all thoſe who adhere unto Him, out of
their Loyalty, and the conſcience of the duty they owed Him: The horrid acts
committed by the barbarous <hi>Iriſh,</hi> in maſſacring the poor
<hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> was ſo ſtrong a motive to
engage people to take armes to ſuppreſſe thoſe <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels,</hi> and
revenge their injuries, that every man was willing to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake that Warre,
little thinking that the deſigne of <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhould onely be made
the pretence, whilſt a <hi>Civill War</hi> in <hi>England</hi> was
principally intended.</p>
            <p>And if men were not ſtupidly ignorant, they might ſtill
diſcerne, that the <hi>Iriſh War</hi> is kept on foot, without intention to
end the ſame by a vigourous undertaking of it, that ſo they may have a
pretence ſtill to leavy and keep Souldiers here in <hi>England,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
to oppreſſe the people by their <hi>Taxes,</hi> and enſlave them by their
<hi>power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For if this had not been their end, why would they not permit
<hi>His Majeſty</hi> who was willing at firſt in Perſon to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take
that War, to be the manager thereof, as it did properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long unto Him? why
did they impoſe ſuch hard conditions on thoſe poor people? wherein the
innocent with the guilty were all involv'd, diſpoſing of their Eſtates,
and ſelling of it to <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant Adventurers,</hi> before they begun the
<hi>War,</hi> thereby rende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the people deſperate, by leaving no gap
open, whereby they might enter by way of <hi>Treaty, mercy</hi> or
<hi>accomodation?</hi> Why doe they now proceed ſo ſlackly in that
<hi>War,</hi> by ſending over inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Forces, and ſtarving
thoſe before they recruit them by freſh ſupplies? or why have they taken
ſuch care, and uſed ſuch induſtry to diſſolve all
<hi>Treaties,</hi> which <hi>His Majesties</hi> pious indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours framed to
compoſe the differences in that Kingdome? un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they intend ſtill to
continue and prolong that War, that ſo they might have ſpecious pretences
from thence to enſlave and poveriſh the people here.</p>
            <p>But now Forces being raiſed for <hi>Ireland,</hi> they did delay
the ſending of them, alleaging that His Majeſty ſeduced by <hi>evill
Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors,</hi> was raiſing an Army to fight againſt the
<hi>Parliament,</hi> and to enthrall His Subjects, depriving them of their
juſt rights and Liberties, and therefore theſe Souldiers with as many more
as they were able to raiſe, muſt be employed to fight againſt the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116917:10"/>
               <hi>Cavelieres,</hi> for with that honourable appellation,
they were plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed malitioufly and ignorantly to ſtile all thoſe, whoſe
Loyalties prompted them to adhere unto <hi>His Majeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being now reſolved upon a War, their next ſtudy was how to be
aſſured of the <hi>ſinewes</hi> thereof, MONEY, and they finde the
certaineſt meanes to be furniſht with that mettall, is to engage the
<hi>City</hi> in their <hi>Rebellion,</hi> whoſe purſes overflow'd with
abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, indirectly gotten by falſe <hi>light Wares, Weights,</hi> and
<hi>Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,</hi> and therefore it was not unlikely that what was gotten by
the cunning of the <hi>Devill,</hi> might be exhauſted to be ſpent by his
<hi>miniſters:</hi> but yet the <hi>knave</hi> &amp; his money are not ſo
ſoone parted as the <hi>foole</hi> and his money, and therefore they muſt
uſe ſome arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall, &amp; cunning ſuggeſtions, to divorce the
<hi>Citizen</hi> from his <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore firſt, they ſell him very cheape pennyworths of
Land in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and having once bit at that bait, and disburſt
ſome money for that purchaſe, it was eaſie to perſwade him to ſhoot
one arrow after another, untill he be drawne by the peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of a faire
ſurvey, with the title confirm'd by an <hi>Ordinance</hi> of
<hi>Parliament,</hi> to buy the <hi>Mannor</hi> of <hi>Hell</hi> with the
<hi>fiſhing</hi> of <hi>Styx,</hi> and the <hi>ferry</hi> of <hi>Charon.</hi>
Elſe who would imagine that there could be a generation of <hi>Chriſtian
people</hi> ſo given over to worke wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe, without any the leaſt
ſhew of legall title, or juſtice for their warrant or ſecurity, that
could be induced to purchaſe other mens Eſtates, nay to purchaſe that
Land which the <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>piety</hi> of our Aunceſtors
conferr'd on the <hi>Church,</hi> nay that theſe <hi>Sacrilegious</hi>
villaines, ravenous birds of prey, can <hi>unplume</hi> the Sacred birds of
<hi>Paradiſe</hi> and <hi>pride</hi> it in their <hi>feathers,</hi>
expoſing the reverend <hi>Clergie</hi> naked to the <hi>frozen</hi> charity
of theſe <hi>unchriſtian</hi> times?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>plenty</hi> are the diſeaſes of this
<hi>City,</hi> and <hi>War</hi> which by bloud-letting cures this
ſickneſſe muſt doe it; but there is a great deale of hazard in it, the
remedy being commonly worſe then the diſeaſe; for ſome time it kils in
ſtead of curing, and moſt times it ſo ruines and deſtroyes the fabrick,
and conſtitution of health, that it leaves a weake, miſerable, and
conſumptive body ever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>In all ages of the world this hath been experimentally
mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted, and I wiſh it may not be prophetically now ſpoken of this
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116917:10"/>City. For all the flouriſhing and moſt famous Cities of
the world, when their <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>luxury</hi> had debaucht them into
ſuch ſins as <hi>London</hi> is guilty of, they have been at laſt
miſerably ſwallowed in the ruines of that War, which their owne
<hi>Rebellion</hi> firſt begot.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Parliament</hi> now had their ends, which was to
engage the <hi>City</hi> as deepely in this <hi>Rebellion</hi> as themſelves;
for ſo they became maſters of their Eſtates, and ſo were enabled to
manage and continue the War at their pleaſures. And truely it was no
difficult taske for them to goe through with their undertaking, for now being
poſſeſt of the money banke (the City mines) they could do all things.</p>
            <p>There the Army is now raiſed, and wants nothing now but a
<hi>popular Generall</hi> to conduct this Army. <hi>Eſſex,</hi> who being
ſcorn'd, laught at, and contemn'd at <hi>Court</hi> amongſt the
<hi>Lords,</hi> for his <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ability,</hi> being angry at his ſlighting,
he was thought fit to be the man, for upon his <hi>Fathers</hi> ſcore, no
<hi>merits</hi> of his <hi>owne,</hi> he was eſteemed amongſt the people:
beſides, he was <hi>bold</hi> and <hi>blockiſh,</hi> ſo his
<hi>confidence</hi> might lead him into <hi>action,</hi> and his
<hi>ignorance</hi> not diſcover their artifice that employ'd him: By this he
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd to be a fit ſubject for their election, and rejection at
plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and accordingly afterward they uſed him, rejected him, and
ſcorn'd him, when he had ſerv'd their turnes.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Army</hi> being now rais'd and marcht, both was done
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſpecious pretext of fighting for the <hi>King,</hi> to bring Him
to His <hi>Parliament,</hi> and to withdraw Him from His <hi>evill
Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors,</hi> to reſide with His <hi>great Councell,</hi> who intended
to make Him a GREAT and GLORIO10</p>
            <p>S KING. A <hi>Battaile</hi> is fought pretended for the
<hi>King,</hi> where <hi>His Majeſty</hi> oppoſed them in Perſon, and
their <hi>undiſtinguiſhable bullets</hi> let flye againſt <hi>His
Majeſty,</hi> the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Yorke,</hi> and
yet all this was ſtill pretended for the <hi>ſafety</hi> of His
<hi>Perſon:</hi> in this <hi>Battaile</hi> it pleaſed <hi>God</hi> to
protect <hi>His Majeſty,</hi> that He came off with <hi>Honour</hi> and
<hi>ſafety,</hi> for He kept the field, tooke divers <hi>Colours,</hi> and
ſome <hi>Cannon.</hi> Yet this muſt be other wayes repreſented to the
<hi>City,</hi> and thoſe who pretended to be in the Battaile, but were indeed
hid in <hi>Sawpits,</hi> muſt be inſtructed to make ample narratives at the
<hi>Guild-Hall,</hi> thereby to gull the City with an opinion of a
<hi>Victory,</hi> leſt they ſhould be diſheartned, and ſo with-hold
their contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:116917:11"/>It is moſt true <hi>His Majesty</hi> loſt
gallant men there, and it could not be otherwiſe, for He had none but ſuch
in His Army, and playing like a prodigall gameſter, <hi>gold</hi> to
<hi>braſſe,</hi> it muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity follow, that by the chance of
War, He muſt loſe ſome of the Nobler mettall, by adventuring it on that
oddes.</p>
            <p>But <hi>His Majeſty</hi> went on with his deſigne, and tooke
<hi>Banbury,</hi> which His enemies durſt not attempt to hinder, and from
thence marcht towards <hi>London,</hi> and having beaten the enemy at
<hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> might undoubtedly have purſued His ſucceſſe into
the <hi>City,</hi> where certainely he had then a ſtrong party to have
aſſiſted Him, but His <hi>Party</hi> reſtrained Him, being unwilling to
expoſe that rich <hi>City,</hi> to the <hi>fury</hi> and <hi>rapine</hi> of
the greedy <hi>Souldier.</hi> His Majeſty therefore retreated unto
<hi>Oxford,</hi> where He might ſtudy that <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gique</hi> which the
<hi>Parliament</hi> had taught Him, which was, how <hi>Subjects</hi> might
fight againſt their <hi>King,</hi> for His preſervation: but finding not
learning enough there to inſtruct Him in this <hi>ſtrange</hi> and
<hi>unheard</hi> of <hi>doctrine,</hi> He takes the field againe, and
ſometimes winnes, and loſes according to the hazard of <hi>Battailes.</hi>
Yet at laſt He grew ſo ſucceſſefull, that our <hi>Brethren</hi> of
<hi>Scotland</hi> were call'd to the aid and aſſiſtance of their
diſtreſſed friends here.</p>
            <p>And now the <hi>ſolemne League</hi> &amp; <hi>Covenant</hi> was
contrived, and theſe accurſed <hi>Traytors</hi> as they had abandoned their
<hi>Loyalty,</hi> ſo they muſt ſweare to forſake their
<hi>Religion,</hi> thereby to engage the <hi>Scots</hi> to their
aſſiſtance. This accordingly they performe, and ſo a
<hi>Scottiſh</hi> Army is brought into the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> hired by
theſe <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcreants</hi> at the price of their <hi>Religion,</hi> to gnaw
out the <hi>bowels</hi> of their <hi>native Country:</hi> by the help of
theſe and their <hi>money,</hi> and by the evill <hi>conduct,</hi> emulating
<hi>pride,</hi> and perfidious <hi>treacherie</hi> of <hi>His Majeſties</hi>
Officers they prevaile, reduce the whole Kingdom to their obedience, and at
laſt purchaſe <hi>His Majeſty</hi> who was fled to the falſe
<hi>Scots</hi> for His protection, and refuge, and by them to the
<hi>diſhonour</hi> of their <hi>Nation</hi> be it ever ſpoken, and with
this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of <hi>ignomy</hi> and <hi>infamy,</hi> let them be branded to
all <hi>poſterity,</hi> who had any ſhare therein: <hi>His Majeſty</hi>
was treacherouſly and <hi>baſely</hi> delivered up into the hands of His
<hi>Rebellious</hi> and <hi>diſloyall</hi> Subjects, who in ſo many
ſeverall <hi>Battailes</hi> had ſought His life, and therefore could not be
imagined but that they would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Him to <hi>contempt,</hi> and as they
have <hi>rob'd</hi> Him of His <hi>Liberty,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:116917:11"/>when they
found it neceſſary or convenient for them, would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive him of his
<hi>life</hi> alſo.</p>
            <p>I have now brought the <hi>Parliament,</hi> or rather they have
brought themſelves to the higheſt degree of <hi>power</hi> and
<hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty;</hi> I beſeech every man ſeriouſly to weigh and
conſider by what meanes and inſtruments they have aſcended to this
<hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame</hi> height, each ſtep by which they have climbed have beene
<hi>multiplied Treaſons,</hi> new in their <hi>invention,</hi> unparallel'd
in their <hi>condition,</hi> ſins of the blackeſt nature have been their
<hi>props</hi> and <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports,</hi> the fowleſt <hi>impieties,</hi> and
the moſt irreligious <hi>practiſes,</hi> the <hi>baſis</hi> and
<hi>foundation</hi> of all their <hi>ſtructure: publique faith</hi> they have
proſtituted like a <hi>common whore,</hi> and taught her to pick the pockets
of her <hi>fornicators: Lying</hi> and <hi>perjury</hi> hath been the
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered <hi>morter</hi> they have <hi>dawb'd</hi> withall: <hi>Murder,
Theft,</hi> and <hi>Rapine,</hi> hath been the chiefe <hi>materials</hi> they
have wrought withall. But leſt you ſhould imagine me too invective,
although I ſpeake nothing but the truth, I will give you my obſervations of
the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, betweene the <hi>preſent</hi> and <hi>preceding</hi> times,
wherein if every indifferent underſtanding be not able to diſcover a
remarkable diſparity, and how we are declin'd into a much worſe condition
then formerly we enjoyed; I muſt conclude he wilfully ſhuts the eyes of his
reaſon, leſt he ſhould be made ſenſible of that igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance he hath
lived in, or be found guilty of conniving at thoſe <hi>plots</hi> and
<hi>practices</hi> which during this <hi>Parliament</hi> have been uſed, to
ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine and deſtroy his Country.</p>
            <p>It were enough to let you ſee the difference, if I onely tell
you the Kingdome before this <hi>Parliament</hi> enjoy'd <hi>peace,</hi> and
that it is now embroyled with a <hi>Civill War:</hi> but I ſhall addreſſe
my ſelfe more particularly to each mans underſtanding; and in the firſt
place I ſhall begin with our <hi>Religion,</hi> which was ſo
<hi>reform'd</hi> and <hi>ſetled</hi> in this Kingdome, as that it was an
<hi>honour</hi> unto our Nation, a <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>terror</hi> unto the
<hi>Romiſh</hi> party, and the hope and wiſh of all <hi>Proteſtant
Churches</hi> beyond the Seas, that they might be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in a capacity to
imitate us; for we had excluded the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell <hi>introductions</hi> and
ſuperſtitious <hi>fopperies</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and yet
retained a <hi>decency</hi> of <hi>order</hi> &amp; <hi>Divine worſhip</hi>
in our <hi>Churches,</hi> ſuch as would not admit of <hi>parity</hi> to
confound, or fancy to diſturbe the wel-compoſed <hi>harmony</hi> in the
<hi>government</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:116917:12"/>That <hi>God,</hi> who is the <hi>God</hi> of
<hi>Order,</hi> and is delighted in it, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares by the conſent and union
in the <hi>Creation,</hi> and diſpoſing of all things, was here ſerved
with <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Reverence; Humility</hi> was the <hi>Garment</hi>
we put on when we entred into the holy places, expreſt by our humble
<hi>Geſtures</hi> and civill <hi>Comportment</hi> in the <hi>time</hi> and
<hi>place</hi> of <hi>Adoration,</hi> and each degree according to his eminency
had that duty and reſpect payed him, which was due according to the
ſuperiority of his calling, from his inferior and ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
Officers.</p>
            <p>A remedy was provided for each inconvenience, and no crime could
eſcape unpuniſhed, unleſſe by the corruption of the Judge, and that
nothing can prevent; for whilſt Jugdes are men, ſome of them will ſtill
be wicked and corrupt, and private paſſions and intereſts will lead them
to connive at offences, or to paſſe indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and unjuſt Sentences,
according to their affections and relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. We had as many eminent and
learned men in the Kingdom as any Age ever produced, and the
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi> and <hi>Innes</hi> of <hi>Court</hi> as flouriſhing
in their ſeverall Profeſſions as ever they were. The <hi>Word</hi> and
the <hi>Sword, Religion</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually
adminiſtred through the Kingdom; each man knew <hi>where,</hi> and
<hi>how</hi> to <hi>pray</hi> according to the Patterne and Forme preſcribed
by our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and to joyne with united hearts and voices in the
moſt ſacred and beſt compoſed <hi>Lyturgie</hi> of the world. The
firſt rudiments of <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> were learned by heart, by
being only Auditors and Aſſiſtans at our <hi>Church</hi> ſervice. The
<hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> the <hi>Greed,</hi> and the <hi>ten Commandements,</hi>
which are the <hi>principles</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> was a part
of our <hi>Lyturgie;</hi> and we are daily taught how to <hi>praiſe God</hi>
for the <hi>benefits</hi> we had and did daily receive, and how to
<hi>pray</hi> unto him for the ſupply of our <hi>wants.</hi> And ſure, on
theſe two maine pillars of <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> the
ſtructure of <hi>Religion</hi> is erected.</p>
            <p>This was the <hi>Sacrifice</hi> we offered three or four times a
day in our <hi>Cathedrals,</hi> and at leaſt as many times a week by
injunction in our ordinary <hi>Churches;</hi> and now this ſacred
<hi>Offertory</hi> which by <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> was
<hi>Enjoyned,</hi> by <hi>Ordinance</hi> is <hi>Aboliſhed,</hi> as if it were
a crime to ſerve <hi>God</hi> in any other forme or method then the two
Houſes ſhall preſcribe. Inſtead of this <hi>Decency</hi> and
<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> what <hi>confuſion</hi> is introduced is obvious to
every man;<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116917:12"/>how theſe divine <hi>Collects</hi> are enforced
to give place to extempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re <hi>Nonſence,</hi> and the admirable compoſed
<hi>Prayers</hi> extracted out of the moſt patheticall parts of the
<hi>Scripture,</hi> muſt be baniſhed the <hi>Church,</hi> whilſt
<hi>Hereſies</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemies</hi> are planted within the walls of
the <hi>Church,</hi> whereby whole <hi>Congregations</hi> are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected and
become <hi>Separatiſts</hi> in their tenents. Pious, Religious, and
<hi>Orthodox</hi> Miniſters are Voted out of their <hi>Free-holds,</hi> and
violently ejected, becauſe they will not be <hi>perjured,</hi> and conforme
to worſhip the <hi>Presbyterian Idol,</hi> or the <hi>Independent
Monſter,</hi> theſe novell <hi>Reformers</hi> would ſet up. And in the
Cures of theſe <hi>Reverend Divines</hi> for the moſt part, ignorant
<hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> and factious <hi>Schiſmatiques</hi> are placed, by
which they have new modell'd the <hi>Church,</hi> and ſetled therein fit
<hi>Chaplains</hi> for ſuch <hi>Patrons,</hi> who muſt inſtruct the
people to believe nothing to be <hi>Orthodox</hi> Divinity but what they read
unto them out of a <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Ordinance,</hi> or a City <hi>Diurnall.</hi>
And if they can but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the people in this ſlaviſh Ignorance, to
forget their duty to <hi>God,</hi> and their <hi>Loyalty</hi> to the
<hi>King,</hi> and to ſubmit by an <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite faith</hi> to the power of
the <hi>Parliament,</hi> then their great work is done; for all their great
labour is to keep up their <hi>Diana</hi> the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and to keep
the people from knowing that it is the <hi>Devill</hi> that utters thoſe
<hi>Oracles</hi> which are vented from that <hi>Shrine.</hi> But ſure the
Bloud of thoſe <hi>Martyrs</hi> who have ſuffered for good Conſciences,
and have either dyed in Priſons, or for want been ſtarved abroad, being
unjuſtly robbed by theſe mercileſſe men of all their Eſtates and
Lively-hoods; cry loud for venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and will one day awaken the patience of
our long ſuffering God: And draw down his revenging wrath on theſe
counterfeit <hi>Zealots,</hi> and impious <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> who have indeed
really no <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> but only make uſe of that ſacred
<hi>Cloak</hi> to diſguiſe all their <hi>villany.</hi> For what have
theſe great <hi>Reformers</hi> done, but introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>will-worſhip</hi>
into the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>Lawleſneſſe</hi> in the
<hi>Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth?</hi> For who can now diſcover the face of any
<hi>Church</hi> in this Kingdome? where every ſeverall Congregation uſe a
diſtinct forme of worſhip, and where there is no <hi>Coercive</hi> power to
compell <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> in <hi>Doctrine,</hi> or to puniſh
<hi>Deformity</hi> in <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</hi> The <hi>ſacred Scripture</hi> is
profaned, and by the <hi>Liberty</hi> each man appropriates to himſelf to
<hi>Interpret</hi> according to his own<pb n="22" facs="tcp:116917:13"/>
               <hi>Fancy,</hi> or
rather to apply that divine writing to ſerve for the advancing his own
deſignes; the ſenſe thereof is ſo inverted by theſe
<hi>Scripturiſts,</hi> who uſe it no other wayes then the <hi>Devill</hi>
did to intrap &amp; circumvent their hearers; ſo that thoſe divine
<hi>Oracles</hi> which were bequeath'd us, to inſtruct us in the right way to
<hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> are by theſe lying Prophets become <hi>by-paths</hi> that
lead to <hi>deſtruction.</hi> Our <hi>Lawes</hi> which are each Subjects
<hi>Birth-right,</hi> how miſerably are they perverted? what man can now be
ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in his inheritance or poſſeſſion, being ſo enſlaved and
ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to an <hi>Arbitrary</hi> power? when by a Vote of the Houſe of
<hi>Commons</hi> we are diſpoſſeſſed of all that we enjoy, and if we
plead our title and appeal to any <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Judicature,</hi>
expecting <hi>Juſtice</hi> according to the known <hi>Lawes</hi> of the Land,
our proceedings are obſtructed by ſome <hi>Order</hi> from the Houſe of
<hi>Commons,</hi> or one of their <hi>Ordinances,</hi> (of which they have made
ſo many, that they know not what they have made; and beſides, diverſe of
them are <hi>contradictory</hi> in themſelves) and by theſe, without
diſpute, we are debard of our <hi>legall Rights.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is now our miſerable condition, that we know not what we
may call our own, or how to preſerve thoſe auncient Inheritances
deſcended from our <hi>Predeceſſors:</hi> for it is in the power of a
<hi>Knave</hi> to ſtile an <hi>Honeſt man</hi> and a <hi>Loyall
Subject</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Malignant</hi> or <hi>Delinquent;</hi> new termes in
the <hi>Law,</hi> invented this bleſſed <hi>Parliament;</hi> and to informe
this under-hand to a <hi>Committee,</hi> where himſelf dares not publickly
appear to avow his <hi>information,</hi> or to be <hi>croſſe
interrogated</hi> concerning his accuſation; and this is ſufficient to
turne a man out of all his Eſtate, expoſe his <hi>Wife</hi> and
<hi>Children</hi> to <hi>beggary,</hi> and no way left to repaire this
injurious proceeding, but by appealing to them that doe the wrong: whence it is
probable you may expect equall juſtice, when your Judges have equally divided
your Eſtate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them: For <hi>Informers</hi> they ſhare with
<hi>Sequeſtrators, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtrators</hi> they ſhare with
<hi>Committee-men,</hi> and <hi>Committee-men</hi> they ſhare with the
<hi>Members</hi> of the Houſe, who are their <hi>great Maſters</hi> that
protect them againſt all <hi>complaints</hi> in the Houſe of
<hi>Commons;</hi> &amp; thus the honeſt <hi>Country-man,</hi> who knew no
offence in maintaning his <hi>Allegeance</hi> which he was bred in, and had
ſworn unto his <hi>King;</hi> is taught by ſuffering to conforme to what he
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:116917:13"/>underſtands not, nor his rulers declare not, the
inſcrutable unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitable <hi>Priviledges</hi> of <hi>Parliament:</hi> from
offending whereof he is no ſooner cleared by ſubmitting to a large Fine,
but that he is preſently ſubject again to the like miſchief, if he obeyes
the <hi>Law</hi> of the Land, or the <hi>malice</hi> of his neighbour
proſecutes him. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels</hi> and <hi>Traytors</hi> ſhall be protected
to rob and plunder by <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and honeſt
men and Loyall Subjects ſhall be ruined and deſtroyed for adhering to the
Eſtabliſhed <hi>Religion</hi> and the known <hi>Lawes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will appeal to every honeſt Country-man, whether he were not
in a much better condition when he was unacquainted with the termes of
<hi>Plunder, Free-quarter,</hi> and <hi>Contribution,</hi> when he underſtood
not the iniquity of a <hi>Sequeſtrator</hi> or a <hi>Committee,</hi> but upon
occaſion of any injury done him, had immediate recourſe to the next
neighbour, the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> where he complained, and
had redreſſe according to a known <hi>Law:</hi> When he went to
<hi>Church,</hi> and knew how to <hi>Pray,</hi> and had <hi>good life</hi> and
<hi>manners</hi> taught him out of the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> and not <hi>Parliament
Orders</hi> and <hi>Declarations</hi> read every <hi>Sunday</hi> which he
underſtands not; when <hi>holy Feaſts</hi> were kept and obſerved, by
which he was taught the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and
<hi>Martyrologie</hi> of the <hi>Saints,</hi> at which time
<hi>Hoſpitality</hi> was obſerved, and thereby <hi>Amity</hi> and
<hi>Friendſhip</hi> maintained and continued amongſt neighbours.</p>
            <p>Theſe were the <hi>bleſſings</hi> of <hi>peace;</hi> what
hath ſucceeded inſtead of this, they have freſh in memory: I need not
particularize, but I am ſure they have, according to the old proverb,
<hi>removed out of Gods bleſſing into the warme Sunne:</hi> for I am ſure
they have changed <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Plenty</hi> into <hi>Warre</hi> and
<hi>Poverty:</hi> by which, as they <hi>ſowed,</hi> they are aſſured to
<hi>reap</hi> the unpleaſant fruits of their labour. I am confident, if men
are not mad, and poſſeſt with ſuch a ſpirit of <hi>Frenſie,</hi> as
that they cannot diſcerne between <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Bad,
Falſe-hood</hi> and <hi>Truth, Religion</hi> and <hi>Irreligion;</hi> they
muſt needs confeſſe, that all they have done or acted for <hi>ſix</hi>
or <hi>ſeaven</hi> yeares laſt paſt, wherein they have complyed with the
<hi>Parliament,</hi> they have endeavoured to advance <hi>evill,
falſe-hood,</hi> and <hi>irreligion,</hi> thereby to deſtroy themſelves
and their Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, and to make themſelves ſlaves to the
<hi>Arbytrary</hi> wills and<pb n="24" facs="tcp:116917:14"/>powers of the <hi>uſurped
Authority</hi> of their <hi>fellow-ſubjects;</hi> by which they are not
maſters of their own Eſtates, but at the wills and pleaſures of thoſe
they have ſet over them. And let them ingenuouſly judge of their own
actions, and then they will confeſſe that they have wilfully perjured
themſelves in forfeiting their <hi>Allegiance</hi> to their
<hi>Soveraigne,</hi> for no <hi>profit</hi> or <hi>advantage</hi> to
themſelves, but to render themſelves in a worſe condition of
<hi>Slavery</hi> and <hi>Vaſſallage</hi> then ever they were in, for now
they are diſpoſable at the wills and pleaſures of their
<hi>fellow-ſubjects,</hi> as their abſolute <hi>Vaſſalls</hi> and
<hi>Slaves,</hi> and can call nothing their own, when they, that is, the
Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> have a deſire to call for it. For this is a
<hi>Maxime</hi> in our new reformed Government, that <hi>all we
poſſeſſe, belongs to the State, and that when the State bath occaſion
to make uſe of it, all is at their diſpoſall.</hi> O happy Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects!
what a bleſſed Government have you fought for! no doubt the whole
Chriſtian world will admire your <hi>Ignorance,</hi> but not follow your
<hi>Example,</hi> for that were to become <hi>fooles</hi> like you, and from
being Subjects <hi>free</hi> and <hi>happy</hi> under a gracious <hi>King,</hi>
to make themſelves <hi>Slaves</hi> to their <hi>Fellow-ſubjects,</hi> as
you have done to M. <hi>Aſh</hi> the <hi>Clothier,</hi> M. <hi>Martin</hi>
the <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> M. <hi>Blackston</hi> the <hi>Pedler,</hi> M.
<hi>Birch</hi> the <hi>Carrier,</hi> &amp; thereſt of the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend rabble,
of which the Houſe of <hi>Comons</hi> is now compoſed. Oh you Subjects of
<hi>England!</hi> if you have any ſenſe of your own miſeries
<hi>entaile</hi> them not to your <hi>Poſterities,</hi> but at length rouze
up your ſelves, &amp; ſhake off the ſervile youk you have drawn in,
returne in zeal to your <hi>God</hi> &amp; his Worſhip, in duty to your
<hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Juſt Rights,</hi> in love to your <hi>Country</hi>
and your <hi>Legall liberty</hi> &amp; vindicate your ſelves from thoſe
aſperſions which now lie heavy on you, and make the <hi>King</hi>
(according to your <hi>Proteſtation</hi>) a <hi>great</hi> and a
<hi>glorious</hi> King, your ſelves free from <hi>Slavery;</hi> &amp; make
the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> know, they are but your <hi>Fellow-ſubjects,</hi>
truſted by you, and that you will call them to an account, wherein they have
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded their Commiſſion.</p>
            <p>And when you dare to become ſo bolde, as to call the
<hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to account for their paſt actions; aske them whether you
gave them any <hi>Authority</hi> to <hi>deſtroy</hi> the <hi>Church,</hi> to
extirpate <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> roote and branch, to aboliſh <hi>Common
Prayer,</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude<pb n="25" facs="tcp:116917:14"/>you from the <hi>bleſſed
Sacraments</hi> of <hi>Baptiſme</hi> and the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> to
introduce a forme of <hi>Marrying</hi> and <hi>Burying</hi> into the
<hi>Church,</hi> fitter for <hi>Pagans</hi> then <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> to
remove the <hi>Ten Comandements,</hi> written with the <hi>Finger</hi> of
<hi>God,</hi> out of the <hi>Church,</hi> and to place inſtead thereof, their
new-invented damned <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant?</hi> After them, whether you gave them
<hi>Authority</hi> to levy <hi>War</hi> againſt your <hi>King,</hi> and to
purſue Him, and endeavour to <hi>kill</hi> Him, becauſe He would not
<hi>perjure</hi> Himſelf by taking that <hi>Covenant,</hi> contrary to the
<hi>Oath</hi> He took at His <hi>Coronation?</hi> Whether you gave them
<hi>Authority</hi> to <hi>impriſon</hi> Him, &amp;c? Aske them, whether you
gave them <hi>Authority</hi> to overthrow all <hi>Lawes,</hi> according to
their <hi>will</hi> and <hi>pleaſure,</hi> and to uſurpe to themſelves,
nay, to <hi>exceede</hi> Regall power, and to <hi>diſpoſe</hi> of your
<hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Eſtates</hi> as they think fit? Ask them for an
<hi>account</hi> of all the <hi>Mony</hi> they have raiſed out of your
Eſtates? Ask them concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all things that have been done amiſſe in
the Kingdome du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their raigne, either by their <hi>command</hi> or
<hi>tolleration;</hi> and if they cannot give you very good ſatisfaction in
all the particulars, proceed againſt them as guilty of the breach of the
truſt you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in them, and puniſh them according to their deſerts;
or if in <hi>Clemency</hi> you think fit to pardon them, at leaſt remove them
from their Rule and Government; and let not thoſe, who have ſo ill behaved
themſelves in the diſcharge of their truſt, be any longer employed by
you, but humbly deſire His Majeſty to call another <hi>Parliament,</hi> and
deſire that you may have free leave to chuſe <hi>new Members,</hi> in
whoſe honeſty you have better hopes. This may be a way to re-ſetle the
Kingdome, and reſtore our <hi>Peace,</hi> elſe we ſhall all be
miſerable: for if theſe <hi>Parliament men</hi> continue to governe us, who
have deſigned themſelves <hi>Princes,</hi> and us their <hi>Slaves,</hi>
what can we expect but by our own conſents, to be made deſpicable?</p>
            <p>It was the cunning of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> when
ſhe intended to become <hi>Catholique,</hi> &amp; rule over all her
<hi>ſiſter Churches,</hi> when ſhe introduced novell
<hi>ſuperſtitions</hi> which ſhe was taxed for, and could not juſtifie;
She ſtill maintained her <hi>errors</hi> by the power ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted her
ſelf withall, which was, that what the <hi>Church</hi> declared either in
<hi>doctrine</hi> or <hi>diſcipline,</hi> ought not to be
<hi>contradicted</hi> or <hi>diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:116917:15"/>for the
<hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> was the ſole <hi>interpreter</hi> of
<hi>Scriptures,</hi> and where they were not able by their <hi>gloſſes</hi>
and <hi>interpretations,</hi> to juſtifie and defend their <hi>Tenents,</hi>
they had un-written <hi>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions,</hi> which on all occaſions ſupported
their <hi>doctrines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is it not ſo with the <hi>Parliament,</hi> I meane the Houſe
of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> for that uſurpes the whole power of the
<hi>Parliament,</hi> (the <hi>Lords</hi> being become no <hi>ciphers</hi> but
<hi>blankes</hi> in their <hi>accounts</hi>) doe not they inveſt themſelves
with a <hi>Soveraigne power,</hi> apropriating <hi>ſole dominion</hi> unto
themſelves, and that nothing is <hi>Law,</hi> but what they declare to be
ſo? and if any act of theirs be queſtioned to be done <hi>contrary</hi> to
the knowne <hi>Law,</hi> have they not an <hi>unknowne Law,</hi> one of their
<hi>unwritten verities,</hi> which are as neceſſary and uſefull as the
<hi>Popiſh traditions,</hi> to juſtifie them in their <hi>erronious</hi>
proceeding? have they not their <hi>Parliament priviledges,</hi> which is their
<hi>Catholocon,</hi> a <hi>medicine</hi> for all diſeaſes, a principall
help at <hi>Mawe,</hi> by which they alwayes with the <hi>prize,</hi> for by
vertue of this miſtery of iniquity, they defend and maintaine all their
ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall actions, and are protected from all inquiry into their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings,
by telling the people <hi>it is a breach of their Priviledges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I wiſh the ſame courſe were taken with the
<hi>Parliament,</hi> that our <hi>Proteſtant Divines</hi> tooke with the
<hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> to enquire when thoſe
<hi>ſuperſtructures</hi> were built in the <hi>Church,</hi> ſo when
theſe <hi>Priviledges</hi> were begotten in the <hi>Parliament;</hi> and then
it would appear, that thoſe <hi>priviledges</hi> were <hi>illegitimate,</hi>
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by <hi>Rebellious parents,</hi> and nurs'd up in <hi>factious</hi>
times, and that the <hi>Law</hi> of the Land neither ownes them, nor knowes
them. Let the <hi>Parliament</hi> be required to produce ſome good authors,
that have aunciently written concerning their <hi>fundamentall Laws,</hi> which
they ſo often mention, and of their <hi>unbounded Priviledges,</hi> which
they ſo often make uſe of: that the people may know that they are not their
owne inventions, that they are not fictions and <hi>chimaer as</hi> to delude
the vulgar, and to <hi>diſguiſe</hi> the <hi>truth,</hi> and bluſter out
their owne <hi>iniquities:</hi> Let them ſhew how an <hi>Ordinance</hi>
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a <hi>Law,</hi> or is able to deſtroy the <hi>Law:</hi> Let them
declare where that <hi>priviledge</hi> is that protects a <hi>Parliament</hi>
man to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit <hi>Fellony,</hi> or <hi>Treaſon,</hi> and that it is a
<hi>breach</hi> of <hi>priviledge</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict him for it. Let them produce
<hi>Records</hi> that are authenticall,<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116917:15"/>that divdes the
<hi>power</hi> from the <hi>Perſon</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> and
<hi>incorporates</hi> that <hi>Power</hi> into the Houſe of <hi>Commons.</hi>
Let them ſhew in any times that the Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> ever
diſpoſed of the <hi>Militia</hi> of the Kingdome, uſurp'd authority to
make <hi>Peace</hi> or <hi>War,</hi> and to contract leagues with forraigne
States, to condemne or pardon, to make Judges to diſpoſe of the <hi>Kings
Revenue,</hi> to Impriſon the <hi>King</hi> Himſelfe, &amp;c. Nay was it
ever heard or read of, that a <hi>Speaker</hi> of the Houſe of
<hi>Commons,</hi> an inconſiderable contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſon for his birth and
breeding, ſhould arrogate to himſelf, and aſſume by the permiſſion
of that Houſe the <hi>enſignes</hi> of <hi>Regall Authority,</hi> and
uſurpe the <hi>Kings Chaire</hi> and cloth of <hi>State,</hi> and give
publique <hi>audience</hi> to <hi>Ambaſſadours?</hi> Oh unheard-of
<hi>arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance,</hi> never to be parallel'd by precedent or future
preſidents, and cannot be exceeded, unleſſe by that of the
<hi>Devill</hi> who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to be <hi>like</hi> the <hi>higheſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let theſe <hi>exorbitances</hi> ſuffice to put the Kingdome in
minde what <hi>preſſures</hi> have been put upon them, what
<hi>uſurpations</hi> the <hi>two Houſes,</hi> (but eſpecially the Houſe
of <hi>Commons</hi>) have injuſtly <hi>arrogated</hi> to themſelves, and
then let them conſider how they are rob'd of their <hi>juſt rights,</hi>
and into what a <hi>ſlavery</hi> they are inthral'd, and whether they have
not <hi>ſlept</hi> thoſe years paſt, whilſt the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> and his
inſtruments have ſown theſe <hi>tares</hi> amongſt their good
<hi>corne,</hi> and ſo ſpoil'd the plentifull <hi>harveſt,</hi> they
hoped to <hi>reape</hi> by this <hi>Parliament;</hi> and that they muſt be
compell'd to hazard to pluck up the <hi>tares,</hi> though therewith the good
<hi>corne</hi> be endange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, for the field muſt be clenſed, to ſow and
prepare for a new <hi>crop,</hi> elſe in a ſhort time the people of this
Kingdome will be <hi>ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> for want of <hi>Bread.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I could enlarge my ſelfe further on this ſubject, for there is
no want of matter to ſwell this diſcourſe into a volume, but I
reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not to make my Country-men more miſerable, by enumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting too
many of their <hi>miſeries,</hi> or by paraphraſing on them,
<hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torically</hi> argue them into too deep a ſenſe of their
<hi>Sufferings;</hi> it ſhall ſuffice me, if they become ſenſible of
their preſent condition, and thereby endeavour a <hi>Manumiſſion</hi>
from their <hi>Slavery,</hi> that they remember what they <hi>were,</hi> what
they <hi>are,</hi> and what they ought to <hi>be,</hi> and as true borne
<hi>Engliſh-men,</hi> ſhake off their<pb n="28" facs="tcp:116917:16"/>
               <hi>Fetters,</hi>
with the ſame hands they have impoſed them, <hi>depoſe</hi> the
<hi>Tyrant Parliament,</hi> and <hi>Re-inthrone</hi> their <hi>lawfull
Soveraigne,</hi> expell <hi>Rebellious Presbytery,</hi> and eſtabliſh
<hi>moderate</hi> and <hi>limited Epiſcopacy,</hi> provide for tender
<hi>conſciences</hi> who will conforme in <hi>obedience</hi> to <hi>Civill
Magiſtracy,</hi> and then no doubt we ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to a ſetled
<hi>Government,</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> will be reſtored with
<hi>plenty,</hi> and we ſhall againe be a happy and united people, as
for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, under our gracious <hi>King,</hi> whom <hi>God</hi> preſerve.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:116917:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
